If I could reveal anything
إذا كان عليَّ أن أكشف عن شيء ما
that is hidden from us,
محجوب عنا
at least in modern cultures,
على الأقل عن الثقافات الحديثة،
it would be to reveal something that we've forgotten,
سيكون عن أمر قد نسيناه
that we used to know
كنا نعرفه
as well as we knew our own names.
تماما كما نعرف أسماءنا.
And that is that we live in a competent universe,
هو أننا نعيش في كون مقتدر،
that we are part of a brilliant planet,
و أننا جزء من كوكب رائع.
and that we are surrounded by genius.
وأننا محاطون بالعباقرة.
Biomimicry is a new discipline
محاكاة الطبيعة (أو البيومميكرية) هو مجال جديد
that tries to learn from those geniuses,
يحاول التعلم من هؤلاء العباقرة,
and take advice from them, design advice.
وأخذ النصائح منهم ، نصائح في مجال التصميم
That's where I live,
هناك حيث أعيش.
and it's my university as well.
وهناك جامعتي أيضا.
I'm surrounded by genius. I cannot help but
أنا محاطة بالعبقرية.حيث لايسعني إلا
remember the organisms and the ecosystems
تذكر الكائنات الحية و النظم الاكولوجية
that know how to live here gracefully on this planet.
التي تعرف كيف تعيش بكل تراحم في هذا الكوكب.
This is what I would tell you to remember
هذا ما أود منكم تذكره
if you ever forget this again.
إن كنتم قد نسيتم مرة أخرى.
Remember this.
تذكروا هذا.
This is what happens every year.
هذا ما يحصل كل سنة.
This is what keeps its promise.
وهذا ما يبقى على وعده.
While we're doing bailouts, this is what happened.
حين كنا ندفع كفالاتنا، هذا ماحصل.
Spring.
فصل الربيع.
Imagine designing spring.
تخيلوا تصميم الربيع.
Imagine that orchestration.
تخيلوا هذا التنظيم.
You think TED is hard to organize. (Laughter) Right?
تظنون أن تنظيم TED صعب ؟(ضحك) أليس كذلك؟
Imagine, and if you haven't done this in a while, do.
تخيلوا، إن لم تكونوا قد فعلتم لبرهة ، تخيلوا.
Imagine the timing, the coordination,
تخيلوا التوقيت ، التنسيق،
all without top-down laws,
دون الأخذ بالاعتبار القوانين المسطرة،
or policies, or climate change protocols.
السياسات، و بروتوكولات تغير المناخ.
This happens every year.
هذا الأمر يحصل كل سنة.
There is lots of showing off.
بكثير من الزهو و التباهي.
There is lots of love in the air.
بكثير من الحب اللامتناهي
There's lots of grand openings.
بكثير من التفتح.
And the organisms, I promise you,
و الكائنات الحية، أؤكد لكم ،
have all of their priorities in order.
لها جميعا أولويات منتظمة.
I have this neighbor that keeps me in touch with this,
لدي هذا الجار ، الذي يطلعني دائما على هذا الأمر.
because he's living, usually on his back,
لأنه يعيش، غالبا على ظهره،
looking up at those grasses.
ينظر عاليا إلى تلك النعم.
And one time he came up to me --
وفي إحدى المرات ، جاء إلي،
he was about seven or eight years old -- he came up to me.
كان في السابعة أو الثامنة من العمر.
And there was a wasp's nest
وكان هناك عش للدبابير
that I had let grow in my yard,
تركته ينمو في فناء منزلي.
right outside my door.
خارج باب المنزل.
And most people knock them down when they're small.
معظم الناس يسحقونهم ، عندما يكونون صغارا.
But it was fascinating to me,
لكن الأمر كان مدهشا بالنسبة لي.
because I was looking at this sort of fine Italian end papers.
لأنني كنت أنظر إلى أوراق الكتب الإيطالية الرفيعة تلك.
And he came up to me and he knocked.
فجاء إلي، و دق بابي.
He would come every day with something to show me.
كان يأتي إلي يوميا يحمل شيئا يريني إياه.
And like, knock like a woodpecker on my door until I opened it up.
فكان مثل... كان يدق الباب مثل نقار الخشب حتى فتحت له.
And he asked me
ثم سألني
how I had made the house for those wasps,
كيف صنعت بيتا لتلك الدبابير.
because he had never seen one this big.
لأنه لم ير قط إحداها بهذا الحجم.
And I told him, "You know, Cody,
فقلت له" هل تعلم يا كودي
the wasps actually made that."
الدبابير هي من صنعت هذا"
And we looked at it together.
ونظرنا إلى هذا سوية.
And I could see why he thought,
وعلمت حينها لماذا فكر كذلك.
you know -- it was so beautifully done.
أتعلمون، لقد كانت مصنوعة بشكل فائق الجمال.
It was so architectural. It was so precise.
كانت هندستها غاية في الدقة.
But it occurred to me, how in his small life
ولكن خطر ببالي، كيف أنه في عالمه الصغير
had he already believed the myth
قد صدق الأسطورة :
that if something was that well done,
أن كل ماصنع بدقة وإتقان،
that we must have done it.
فإنه بالضرورة من صنعنا.
How did he not know --
كيف أنه لم يكن يعلم،
it's what we've all forgotten --
إنه الأمر الذي نسيناه جميعا،
that we're not the first ones to build.
أننا لمن نكن أول من بنى.
We're not the first ones to process cellulose.
أننا لمن نكن أول من اكتشف السليولوز.
We're not the first ones to make paper. We're not the first ones
أننا لمن نكن أول من صنع الورق.لسنا أول من
to try to optimize packing space,
حاول استعمال موارد التعبئة بشكل افضل،
or to waterproof, or to try to heat and cool a structure.
أو صنع واقيات من الماء ، أو تبريد و تسخين بنية ما.
We're not the first ones to build houses for our young.
لسنا أول من بنى مساكن لصغارنا.
What's happening now, in this field called biomimicry,
ما يحدث الآن ، في هذا المجال المسمى " محاكاة الطبيعة"،
is that people are beginning to remember
أن الناس بدأوا يتذكرون
that organisms, other organisms,
أن الكائنات الحية ، الكائنات الحية الأخرى،
the rest of the natural world,
ماتبقى من العالم الطبيعي،
are doing things very similar to what we need to do.
تصنع أشياء تشبه إلى حد كبير ، ما علينا القيام به.
But in fact they are doing them in a way
لكنها في الواقع تفعل ذلك بشكل
that have allowed them to live gracefully on this planet
مكنها من العيش بتناغم في هذا الكوكب
for billions of years.
لمليارات السنين.
So these people, biomimics,
إذن فهؤلاء الناس ، محاكو الطبيعة،
are nature's apprentices.
تلاميذ للطبيعة.
And they're focusing on function.
يركزون على دراسة وظائفها.
What I'd like to do is show you a few of the things
و ما أود فعله ، هو أن أريكم بعض الأشياء
that they're learning.
مما تعلموه.
They have asked themselves,
سألوا أنفسهم،
"What if, every time I started to invent something,
"ماذا لو ، في كل مرة أبدأ فيها اختراع شيء ما
I asked, 'How would nature solve this?'"
ابدأ بالسؤال :كيف كانت الطبيعة ستحل هذا الأمر؟"
And here is what they're learning.
وإليكم شيئا مما تعلموه.
This is an amazing picture from a Czech photographer named Jack Hedley.
هذه صورة مدهشة لمصور تشيكي اسمه جاك هيدلي.
This is a story about an engineer at J.R. West.
هذه قصة عن مهندس في السكك الحديدية اليابانية.
They're the people who make the bullet train.
إنهم الأشخاص الذين يصنعون قطار الرصاص.
It was called the bullet train
وقد سمي بقطار الرصاص،
because it was rounded in front,
لأنه دائري عند المقدمة.
but every time it went into a tunnel
لكن في كل مرة يمر عبر النفق
it would build up a pressure wave,
قد يخلق موجة من الضغط.
and then it would create like a sonic boom when it exited.
ومن ثم يخلق ما يشبه صوتا مدويا عند خروجه.
So the engineer's boss said,
حينها قال كبير المهندسين،
"Find a way to quiet this train."
"جِدوا طريقة ما لإسكات هذا القطار"
He happened to be a birder.
وقد صدف أنه بنفسه خبير طيور.
He went to the equivalent of an Audubon Society meeting.
وكان أن ذهب إلى ما يعادل "مؤتمر أودوبون الاجتماعي".
And he studied -- there was a film about king fishers.
ودرس، كان هناك فيلم عن ملك الصيادين.
And he thought to himself, "They go from one density of medium,
ففكر في نفسه" إنهم ليمرون من كثافة متوسطة,
the air, into another density of medium, water,
الهواء، ثم كثافة متوسطة، ماء،
without a splash. Look at this picture.
دون أن يخوضوا في الماء. انظروا إلى هذه الصورة.
Without a splash, so they can see the fish.
دون أن يخوضوا في الماء لكي يروا السمكة.
And he thought, "What if we do this?"
ثم فكر : " ماذا لو فعلنا مثل هذا الأمر؟"
Quieted the train.
لإسكات القطار.
Made it go 10 percent faster on 15 percent less electricity.
وجعله أسرع بنسبة 10% بمعدل خفض للطاقة يعادل 15% .
How does nature repel bacteria?
كيف تصد الطبيعة البكتيريا عنها؟
We're not the first ones to have to protect ourselves
لسنا أول من كان عليهم المحافظة على أنفسهم
from some bacteria.
من بعض البكتيريا.
Turns out that -- this is a Galapagos Shark.
اتضح أنه-- هذا قرش غلاباغوس.
It has no bacteria on its surface, no fouling on its surface, no barnacles.
اتضح أنه، لا توجد عليه أية بكتيريا ، أوساخ أوأسماك قشرية.
And it's not because it goes fast.
ليس لأنه سريع.
It actually basks. It's a slow-moving shark.
بل لأنه يتدفأ بالشمس ، إنه قرش بطيء.
So how does it keep its body free of bacteria build-up?
إذن فكيف يبقي على جسمه خاليا من البكتيريا؟
It doesn't do it with a chemical.
لا يفعل هذا عن طريق مواد كيماوية.
It does it, it turns out, with the same denticles
اتضح أنه يفعل ذلك عن طريق نفس الأسنان الصغيرة
that you had on Speedo bathing suits,
التي تجدونها في مجموعات "سبيدو" للسباحة،
that broke all those records in the Olympics,
و التي حطمت جميع الأرقام القياسية الأولمبية.
but it's a particular kind of pattern.
إنه نمط خاص نوعا ما.
And that pattern, the architecture of that pattern
و هندسة هذا النمط،
on its skin denticles
أن على جلده أسنان صغيرة
keep bacteria from being able to land and adhere.
تمنع الجراثيم من البقاء.
There is a company called Sharklet Technologies
هناك شركة تدعى :شاركلت تكنولوجيز
that's now putting this on the surfaces in hospitals
تضع على هذا النمط على أسطح المستشفيات
to keep bacteria from landing,
لتمنع البكتريا من التكاثر .
which is better than dousing it with anti-bacterials or harsh cleansers
مما يجعله أفضل من إغراق الأسطح بمضادات البكتريا أو المنظفات القاسية
that many, many organisms are now becoming drug resistant.
التي أصبحت العديد من الكائنات الحية مقاومة لها.
Hospital-acquired infections are now killing
تقتل العدوى التي تنتقل في المستشفيات الآن
more people every year in the United States
مزيدا من الأشخاص سنويا، في الولايات المتحدة،
than die from AIDS or cancer or car accidents combined --
أكثر مما يسببه الايدز، وحوادث السيارات مجتمعة،
about 100,000.
ما يعادل 100 ألف شخص.
This is a little critter that's in the Namibian desert.
هناك مخلوق يعيش في صحراء ناميبيا.
It has no fresh water that it's able to drink,
و ما من ماء عذب يمكنه شربه.
but it drinks water out of fog.
لكنه يشرب الماء المستمد من الضباب.
It's got bumps on the back of its wing covers.
إذ توجد لديه ثقوب على ظهر جناحيه.
And those bumps act like a magnet for water.
تعمل كمغناطيس للمياه.
They have water-loving tips, and waxy sides.
ولديه خاصية الجزيئات المحبة للماء ، و أطراف شمعية.
And the fog comes in and it builds up on the tips.
فيأتي الضباب و يبني على هذه الخاصيات.
And it goes down the sides and goes into the critter's mouth.
فينزل على الجانبين ، و يدخل إلى فم هذا المخلوق.
There is actually a scientist here at Oxford
هناك في الواقع عالم هنا في أوكسفورد
who studied this, Andrew Parker.
درس هذا الأمر ،أندرو باركر.
And now kinetic and architectural firms like Grimshaw
و الآن هناك شركات للهندسة مثل شركة " كريمشاو"
are starting to look at this as a way
بدأت ترى في هذا الأمر طريقة
of coating buildings
لتغليف البنايات
so that they gather water from the fog.
بحيث تستخلص الماء من الضباب.
10 times better than our fog-catching nets.
وهذه الطريقة أفضل ب 10 أضعاف من الشبكات المجمعة للماء من الضباب.
CO2 as a building block.
ثنائي أوكسيد الكاربون كلَبِنة بناء.
Organisms don't think of CO2 as a poison.
لا تعتبر الكائنات الحية ثنائي أوكسيد الكاربون سمّاً.
Plants and organisms that make shells,
النباتات و الكائنات الحية التي تصنع الصدفات،
coral, think of it as a building block.
أو المرجان،تعتبره لَبِنة بناء.
There is now a cement manufacturing company
هناك الآن شركة لصناعة الإسمنت
starting in the United States called Calera.
أنشأت في الولايات المتحدة ، تسمى "كلارا".
They've borrowed the recipe from the coral reef,
استعارت الوصفة من الشعب المرجانية.
and they're using CO2 as a building block
و هم الآن يستعملون ثنائي أوكسيد الكاربون كلَبِنة بناء
in cement, in concrete.
من الأسمنت، بشكل ملموس.
Instead of -- cement usually
غالبا ما يصدر الإسمنت
emits a ton of CO2 for every ton of cement.
طنا واحدا من ثنائي أكسيد الكربون عن كل طن من الإسمنت.
Now it's reversing that equation,
أما الآن فالمعادلة قد قلبت،
and actually sequestering half a ton of CO2
بخفض معدل انبعاث ثنائي أكسيد الكربون إلى نصف طن
thanks to the recipe from the coral.
بفضل الوصفة المقدمة من طرف الشعب المرجانية.
None of these are using the organisms.
مامن أحد يستعمل الكائنات الحية في هذا الأمر.
They're really only using the blueprints or the recipes
إنهم يستعملون فقط التصاميم أو الوصفات
from the organisms.
المستوحاة من هذه الكائنات.
How does nature gather the sun's energy?
كيف تستطيع الطبيعة تجميع الطاقة الشمسية؟
This is a new kind of solar cell
هذا نوع جديد من الخلايا الشمسية
that's based on how a leaf works.
يعتمد على كيفية عمل أوراق الأشجار.
It's self-assembling.
حيث تجمع نفسها بنفسها.
It can be put down on any substrate whatsoever.
ويمكن وضعها على أي ركيزة ضخ.
It's extremely inexpensive
وهي بخسة الثمن
and rechargeable every five years.
و يتم شحنها كل 5 سنوات.
It's actually a company a company that I'm involved in called OneSun,
إنها في الواقع ، الشركة التي أعمل فيها ، و تدعى : OneSun ،
with Paul Hawken.
مع پول هاوكن.
There are many many ways that nature filters water
هناك طرق عديدة جدا تستخدمها الطبيعة لتصفية الماء
that takes salt out of water.
أو لتحليته،
We take water and push it against a membrane.
نأخذ الماء و ندفعه من خلال أغشية
And then we wonder why the membrane clogs
ثم بتنا نتساءل لماذا بدأت ثقوب هذه الأغشية بالانسداد
and why it takes so much electricity.
ولماذا تُستهلك الطاقة في هذا الأمر بهذا الشكل الكبير؟
Nature does something much more elegant.
تقوم الطبيعة بهذه العملية بطريقة غاية في الأناقة.
And it's in every cell.
وهذا الأمر موجود في كل خلية.
Every red blood cell of your body right now
كل كرية دم حمراء في جسمكم الآن
has these hourglass-shaped pores
لها مسام على شكل ساعة رملية
called aquaporins.
تدعى الأكواپورين.
They actually export water molecules through.
تصدر جزيئات الماء من خلالها.
It's kind of a forward osmosis.
في شكل أشبه بالتنافذ الأمامي.
They export water molecules through,
تصدر جزيئات الماء عبرها،
and leave solutes on the other side.
و تترك المواد المذابة جانبا.
A company called Aquaporin is starting to make desalination
شرعت شركة تدعى أكواپورين بصنع أغشية
membranes mimicking this technology.
لتحلية المياه محاكية بذلك هذه التكنولوجيا.
Trees and bones are constantly reforming themselves
تقوم الأشجار و العظام بتقويم نفسها بنفسها باستمرار
along lines of stress.
على طول خطوط التوتر.
This algorithm has been put into a software program
وقد تم وضع هذه الخوارزمية في أحد البرامج
that's now being used to make bridges lightweight,
يستخدم الآن لصناعة جسور خفيفة الوزن,
to make building beams lightweight.
لجعل حزمة البناء خفيفة الوزن.
Actually G.M. Opel used it
في الواقع جنرال موتور أوپل استعملت هذا الأمر
to create that skeleton you see,
لإنشاء هذا الهيكل الذي ترون،
in what's called their bionic car.
في ما يسمى سيارتهم ذات الأعضاء الآلية.
It lightweighted that skeleton using a minimum amount of material,
ذلك أنها تخفف وزن ذلك الهيكل باستخدام الحد الأدنى من المواد،
as an organism must,
بالمقارنة مع ما يتطلبه جسم عضوي،
for the maximum amount of strength.
بأقصى قدر ممكن من القوة.
This beetle, unlike this chip bag here,
هذه الخنفساء، على عكس كيس رقائق البطاطس هذا هنا،
this beetle uses one material, chitin.
هذه الخنفساء، تستخدم مادة واحدة ، الكيتين.
And it finds many many ways
و هي تجد طرقا عديدة جدا
to put many functions into it.
لاستخدامها لعدة وظائف.
It's waterproof.
إنها مقاومة للماء.
It's strong and resilient.
قوية ومرنة.
It's breathable. It creates color through structure.
هي كذلك تتنفس، و تخلق ألوانا من خلال بنية معينة.
Whereas that chip bag has about seven layers to do all of those things.
في حين أن حقيبة رقاقة البطاطس تحتاج إلى حوالي سبع طبقات للقيام بكل تلك الأمور.
One of our major inventions
واحدة من أهم اختراعاتنا
that we need to be able to do
التي نحتاجها لنتمكن من
to come even close to what these organisms can do
الاقتراب مما تقوم به الكائنات الحية
is to find a way
هو أن نجد طريقة ما
to minimize the amount of material, the kind of material we use,
للتقليل من كمية المواد التي نستخدمها و نوعيتها،
and to add design to it.
وإضافة تصاميم عليها.
We use five polymers in the natural world
تستخدم خمس مركبات كيميائية في العالم الطبيعي
to do everything that you see.
للحصول على كل تشاهدونه الآن.
In our world we use about 350 polymers
نستعمل في عالمنا 350 مكوثرا ( بوليمر)
to make all this.
لصناعة كل هذا.
Nature is nano.
الطبيعة هي نانو.
Nanotechnology, nanoparticles, you hear a lot of worry about this.
تكنولوجيا النانو ، النانوية، تسمعون الكثيرعن المخاوف المحيطة بهذه الأمور .
Loose nanoparticles. What is really interesting to me
نانونية غير منظمة. ما يهمني حقيقة في الأمر
is that not many people have been asking,
هو أن فئة قليلة من الناس تساءلت
"How can we consult nature about how to make nanotechnology safe?"
"كيف يمكننا استشارة الطبيعة حول كيفية جعل تكنولوجيا النانو تكنولوجيا أمنة ؟"
Nature has been doing that for a long time.
لطالما فعلت الطبيعة ذلك منذ فترة طويلة.
Embedding nanoparticles in a material for instance, always.
كتضمين النانونية في المواد ، على سبيل المثال.
In fact, sulfur-reducing bacteria,
في الواقع، فالبكتيريا مختزلة الكبريت،
as part of their synthesis,
و كجزء من تجميعها،
they will emit, as a byproduct,
ستصدر ، كمنتج ثانوي،
nanoparticles into the water.
جسيمات نانونية في الماء.
But then right after that, they emit a protein
ولكن فورا بعد ذلك ستصدر بروتينا
that actually gathers and aggregates those nanoparticles
سيجمع و يُجمِل هذه الجسيمات النانونية
so that they fall out of solution.
بحيث تسقط من المحلول.
Energy use. Organisms sip energy,
استخدام الطاقة . ترشف الكائنات الحية الطاقة.
because they have to work or barter for every single bit that they get.
لأن عليهم العمل أو مقايضة بكل جزء يحصلون عليه.
And one of the largest fields right now,
وواحدة من أكبر الحقول في الوقت الراهن ،
in the world of energy grids,
في عالم شبكات الطاقة،
you hear about the smart grid.
لا بد أنكم سمعتم عن الشبكة الذكية.
One of the largest consultants are the social insects.
واحدة من أكبر الاستشاريين هي الحشرات الاجتماعية.
Swarm technology. There is a company called Regen.
تكنولوجيا السرب. هناك شركة تدعى ريجين.
They are looking at how ants and bees
تبحث الآن كيف أن النمل و النحل
in the most effective way
بطريقة غاية في الفعالية
as a whole hive.
كخلية بأكملها.
And they're having appliances in your home
ولها أجهزة داخل منازلكم
talk to one another through that algorithm,
تتحدث مع بعضها البعض من خلال هذه الخوارزمية،
and determine how to minimize peak power use.
وتحدد كيفية تقليل استخدام طاقة الذروة.
There's a group of scientists in Cornell
هناك مجموعة من العلماء في جامعة كورنيل
that are making what they call a synthetic tree,
يحاولون صنع ما يسمونه شجرة اصطناعية.
because they are saying, "There is no pump at the bottom of a tree."
لأنهم يقولون، "لا توجد مضخة في الجزء السفلي من الشجر".
It's capillary action and transpiration pulls
إنه نشاط مثل نشاط الشعر، ترفع الماء
water up, a drop at a time,
المرتشف ، قطرةً قطرة.
pulling it, releasing it from a leaf and pulling it up through the roots.
تسحبه، تستخلصه من الورقة ثم ترفعه من خلال الجذور.
And they're creating -- you can think of it as a kind of wallpaper.
و هم يصنعون --يمكنكم أن تعتبروه نوعا من ورق الحائط.
They're thinking about putting it on the insides of buildings
وهم يفكرون في وضعه داخل المباني
to move water up without pumps.
لنقل المياه من دون مضخات.
Amazon electric eel -- incredibly endangered,
سمك الإنقليس الذي يعيش في الأمازون، مهدد الآن بخطورة،
some of these species --
بعض من هذه الأنواع ،
create 600 volts of electricity
تقوم بخلق 600 فولت من الكهرباء
with the chemicals that are in your body.
عن طريق بعض المواد الكيميائية التي توجد داخل جسمكم.
Even more interesting to me is that
و ماأعتبره مثيرا للاهتمام في رأيي
600 volts doesn't fry it.
أن هذه الكمية من الطاقة لا تحرقه.
You know we use PVC, and we sheath wires
تعلمون أننا نستعمل البلاستيك. و نغمد الأسلاك
with PVC for insulation.
بالبلاستيك من أجل عزلها.
These organisms, how are they insulating
بالنسبة لهذه الكائنات الحية، كيف تتمكن من عزل جسمها
against their own electric charge?
من الشحنة الكهربائية التي يصدرونها؟
These are some questions that we've yet to ask.
هذه هي بعض الأسئلة التي علينا أن نطرحها.
Here's a wind turbine manufacturer that went to a whale.
هذا مصِّنع لمحركات الريح استقى فكرة من الحوت.
Humpback whale has scalloped edges on its flippers.
لدى الحوت الأحدب حواف صدفية على زعانفها.
And those scalloped edges
وهذه الحواف الصدفية
play with flow in such a way
تلاعب التيار بطريقة
that is reduces drag by 32 percent.
تقلل من الانجراف بنسبة 32%.
These wind turbines can rotate in incredibly slow windspeeds, as a result.
إذن فيمكن لمحركات الرياح هاته أن تتحرك بشكل غاية في البطء مهما بلغت سرعة الرياح، نتيجة لذلك.
MIT just has a new radio chip
اكتشف معهد ماساتشوستس للتكنولوجيا رقاقة راديو جديدة
that uses far less power than our chips.
تستخدم طاقة أقل بكثير من الرقائق التي نستعملها.
And it's based on the cochlear of your ear,
وهي توضع داخل قوقعة أذنكم،
able to pick up internet, wireless, television signals
وهي قادرة على التقاط إشارات الانترنت ،اللاسلكي و التلفاز،
and radio signals, in the same chip.
وإشارات الراديو،كل هذا على الرقاقة ذاتها.
Finally, on an ecosystem scale.
وأخيرا، على مستوى الأنظمة الإيكولوجية.
At Biomimicry Guild, which is my consulting company,
في" بيوميميكري كيلد" و هي شركتي الخاصة للاستشارات،
we work with HOK Architects.
نعمل مع مهندسين من شركة "هوك"،
We're looking at building whole cities
ونتطلع إلى بناء مدن كاملة،
in their planning department.
مع فريق التخطيط الخاص بهم.
And what we're saying is that,
وما نقوله هو أن،
shouldn't our cities do at least as well,
ألا ينبغي على مدننا أن تكون أفضل حالا ، على الأقل ،
in terms of ecosystem services,
من حيث خدمات النظام الإيكولوجي ،
as the native systems that they replace?
كما كان الحال عليه في النظم التي حلت مكانها؟
So we're creating something called Ecological Performance Standards
لذلك نحن خلق ما يسمى معايير الأداء البيئي،
that hold cities to this higher bar.
لإنقاء المدن ضمن هذه المعايير العالية.
The question is -- biomimicry is an incredibly powerful
والسؤال هو -- محاكاة الطبيعة مجال ضخم جدا
way to innovate.
طريق إلى الابتكار.
The question I would ask is, "What's worth solving?"
السؤال الذي أود طرحه هو :" مالذي يستحق فعلا أن نجد له حلا؟"
If you haven't seen this, it's pretty amazing.
إن كنتم لم تروا هذا..إنه لأمر مدهش جدا.
Dr. Adam Neiman.
الدكتور آدم نيمان.
This is a depiction of
هذا رسم يوضح
all of the water on Earth
المياه على الأرض
in relation to the volume of the Earth --
بالنسبة لحجم الأرض
all the ice, all the fresh water, all the sea water --
كل الجليد، وجميع المياه العذبة ، وجميع مياه البحر،
and all the atmosphere that we can breathe, in relation to the volume of the Earth.
وجميع الهواء الذي نتنفسه، بالنسبة إلى حجم الأرض.
And inside those balls
وداخل تلك الكرات
life, over 3.8 billion years,
صنعت الحياة، على مر 3.8 مليار سنة،
has made a lush, livable place for us.
مكانا خصبا و صالحا لنعيش فيه.
And we are in a long, long line
و نحن الآن على صف طويل جدا
of organisms
من الكائنات الحية
to come to this planet and ask ourselves,
لنأتي إلى هذا الكوكب ، و نسأل أنفسنا،
"How can we live here gracefully over the long haul?"
"كيف يمكننا العيش هنا بأمان على المدى الطويل؟"
How can we do what life has learned to do?
كيف يمكننا أن نفعل ما تعلمت الحياة فعله؟
Which is to create conditions conducive to life.
وهو خلق الظروف المواتية للحياة.
Now in order to do this, the design challenge
الآن من أجل القيام بهذا : تحدي تصميم
of our century, I think,
القرن الذي نعيشه، في اعتقادي،
we need a way to remind ourselves of those geniuses,
نحن بحاجة إلى وسيلة لتذكير أنفسنا بأولئك العباقرة،
and to somehow meet them again.
وبطريقة أو بأخرى لقاؤهم مرة أخرى.
One of the big ideas, one of the big projects
واحدة من الأفكار الكبيرة، واحدة من المشاريع الكبرى
I've been honored to work on
تشرفت بالعمل عليها
is a new website. And I would encourage you all to please go to it.
هوموقع جديد. وأود أن أشجعكم جميعا للذهاب لزيارته.
It's called AskNature.org.
يسمىAskNature.org.
And what we're trying to do, in a TEDesque way,
وما نحاول القيام به ، على غرار TED،
is to organize all biological information
هو تنظيم جميع المعلومات البيولوجية
by design and engineering function.
حسب وظائفها التصميمية و الهندسية.
And we're working with EOL, Encyclopedia of Life,
ونحن نعمل مع دائرة معارف الحياة، موسوعة الحياة ،
Ed Wilson's TED wish.
و هي أمنية إد ويلسون.
And he's gathering all biological information
فهو يقوم بجمع كل المعلومات البيولوجية
on one website.
على موقع واحد.
And the scientists who are contributing to EOL are answering a question,
والعلماء الذين يساهمون في دائرة معارف الحياة يجيبون على سؤال واحد.
"What can we learn from this organism?"
"ماذا يمكننا أن نتعلم من هذا الكائن الحي؟"
And that information will go into AskNature.org.
فتجمع هذه المعلومات على موقع AskNature.org.
And hopefully, any inventor, anywhere in the world,
ونأمل، أن أي مخترع، في أي مكان في العالم ،
will be able, in the moment of creation,
سيكون قادرا ، في لحظة تنفيذ الاختراع،
to type in, "How does nature remove salt from water?"
أن يكتب على الموقع : "ماذا فعلت الطبيعة لإزالة الملح من المياه؟"
And up will come mangroves, and sea turtles
وسوف تصل أشجار المانغروف والسلاحف البحرية،
and your own kidneys.
و الكليتان.
And we'll begin to
وسوف نصبح
be able to
قادرين على
do as Cody does,
فعل ما يقوم به كودي،
and actually be in touch
و نكون على اتصال مع
with these incredible models,
مع هذه النماذج المدهشة،
these elders that have been here
هؤلاء الشيوخ الذين كانوا هنا
far, far longer than we have.
فترة أطول منا.
And hopefully, with their help,
و نأمل، بمساعدتهم،
we'll learn how to live on this Earth,
سنتعلم كيف نعيش على هذه الأرض،
and on this home that is ours, but not ours alone.
في هذا البيت الذي هو ملك لنا ، و لكن ليس ملكا لنا وحدنا.
Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)